Guide to the Jeffrey Gerson Brooklyn politics research collection 2013.021
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Herbert Lupka, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 1, Box 9, Cassette 34, Cassette 35)
  Herbert "Herb" Lupka was from Kings Highway, Brooklyn. He was a Brooklyn assembly district leader and First Deputy Supreme Court Kings County Clerk. Lupka died in 2018.
  This interview took place on September 11, 1987 at Herbert Lupka's office in Brooklyn. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  Four preservation .WAV files. Four access .mp3 files.
- Madison Club, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Joseph Mahood, circa 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- James Mangano, 1965-1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- James Mangano, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 5, Box 9, Cassette 36, Cassette 37)
  James V. Mangano was born on November 21, 1905. Mangano was elected as a New York State Assemblymember in 1934 and in 1938 was elected to be Kings County Sheriff. He was the last person to serve as Kings County Sheriff because the position was dissolved in 1942 and replaced by a New York City-wide Sheriff position. Mangano then served as administrative assistant to several New York State Supreme Court Justices and then was administrative director of the New York State Supreme Court in Brooklyn from 1954 to 1975. Mangano died on October 28, 1988.
  This interview took place on September 16, 1987. The audio includes comments from Jeffrey Gerson after the interview. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  Gerson's audio comments after meeting with James Mangano are on one preservation .WAV file and one access .mp3 file.
- Robert Mangum, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Joan Maynard, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 7, Box 9, Cassette 38)
  Joan Maynard was born on August 29, 1928 in Brooklyn. She graduated from Empire State College of the State University of New York. She then worked as an artist for companies such as McGraw-Hill and drew covers for Crisis, a publication of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP). Maynard founded and was the first executive director of the Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History (now the Weeksville Heritage Center). Maynard was also a member of the Unity Democratic Club. Maynard died on January 23, 2006.
  This interview took place on September 19, 1989 at the Weeksville Society in Brooklyn. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Harold J. McLaughlin, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 8, Box 9, Cassette 39)
  Harold McLaughlin was born in the Bronx on June 22, 1905. He moved to Brooklyn Heights in Brooklyn in 1927 and then to Marine Park also in Brooklyn where he lived for the majority of his life. McLaughlin was a judge of the Municipal Court and State Supreme Court in Brooklyn. McLaughlin died in 1993.
  This interview took place on July 28, 1987 at Harold McLaughlin's office in Brooklyn. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Mobilization for Youth, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- John H. Mollenkopf, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  This file contains photocopies of "The Wagner Atlas: New York City Politics 1989" by John H. Mollenkopf.
- Moorland-Spingarn Research Center, 1970-1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Franklin Morton, circa 1989 (Box 4, Folder 12, Box 9, Cassette 40, Cassette 41)
  Franklin Wheeler Morton, Jr. was born on May 20, 1920 at Lincoln Settlement House in Downtown Brooklyn. Morton started law school at Temple University, but his studies were interrupted when he served in the U.S. Army during World War II. He finished law school at St. John's University. He was appointed to the Municipal Court in Brooklyn in 1958 and then was elected to the New York State Supreme Court in 1969. Morton was a member of Bertram Baker's United Action Democratic Political Club.
  Morton's grandmother was Verina Morton Jones, the first woman to practice medicine in the state of Mississippi and a co-founder of Lincoln Settlement House.
  Morton died on October 28, 2014.
  This interview took place on February 17, 1988 at Morton's home in Brooklyn. The audio from this interview also includes Gerson's comments after the first part of the interview. This interview is accompanied by a partial transcript.
- Abraham Multer, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 13 - 14)
- Albert Murray, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 15-17, Box 9, Cassette 42, Cassette 43)
  Albert R. Murray was born on March 15, 1921 in Harlem, Georgia. Murray served in World War II, then received his B.A. from Long Island University and his law degree from Brooklyn Law School. He was a member of Bertram L. Baker's United Action Democratic Club and a partner in the law firm Kaufman and Murray. Murray and his wife Odetta opened Hillside Inn, a resort in the Poconos, in 1954. He was Assistant District Attorney and was then appointed to the Brooklyn Criminal Court in 1965 by Mayor Robert Wagner. Murray was the first Black judge to hold this position. He then became a New York State Supreme Court Justice. He retired from the Court in 1983 and moved to the Poconos permanently. Murray died on October 21, 2005.
  This interview took place on July 9, 1988 at Albert Murray's home in East Stroudsburg, Pennsylvania. Odetta Murray, Albert Murray's wife sat in on the interview. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1955 - circa 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Leon Nelson, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 19, Box 9, Cassette 44)
  Leon "Nellie" Nelson was born on November 5, 1915 on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. His family moved to Coney Island when he was five years old. Nelson joined the Young Communist League in Brighton Beach and helped organize cellar clubs in Brighton Beach in the mid 1930s. Nelson was a Communist Party candidate for New York State Kings County 2nd Assembly District in 1940. Nelson died in 1995.
  This interview took place on April 26, 1988. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Jack Newfield, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  This file contains photocopies of the New York Magazine article "Robert Kennedy's Bedford-Stuyvesant Legacy" by Jack Newfield.
- New York City obituaries, 1953-1992 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- 1964 New York City riots, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Paul O'Dwyer, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Paul O'Dwyer, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 24, Box 9, Cassette 45)
  Paul O'Dwyer was born on June 29, 1907 in Ireland. He moved to New York City when he was 18 and later attended Fordham University and St. John's University Law School. His brother was William O'Dwyer, who served as Mayor of New York City 1946-1950. O'Dwyer was President of the New York City Council from 1974 to 1977 and was a partner in the O'Dwyer and Bernstein law firm. He supported the Irish Republican Army and Israeli sovereignty. O'Dwyer died on June 23, 1998.
  This interview took place on November 12, 1993 at Paul O'Dwyer's home in Goshen, New York. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- William O'Dwyer, circa 1986 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- William O'Dwyer, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Joseph Orlando, circa 1989 (Box 4, Folder 27, Box 9, Cassette 46, Cassette 47)
  Joseph J. Orlando was born on July 27, 1904 and grew up in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. His father was New York City Harbor Master. Orlando was a political leader in the 4th Assembly District in Williamsburg and worked with the Lentol family in local politics. Orlando died on May 12, 1992.
  This interview took place on February 29, 1989. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Dorothy Orr, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 28, Box 9, Cassette 48, Cassette 49)
  Dorothy James Orr was born on January 12, 1920 in Meadville, Pennsylvania. She graduated from Allegheny College and then from Atlanta University with her master's degree in social work. Orr worked for the Equitable Life Assurance Society and was executive director of Youth in Action and HARYOU ACT (Harlem Youth Opportunities Associated Community Teams). Orr taught at Fordham University and received an honorary doctorate from Pace University in 2005. Orr died in 2015.
  This interview took place on July 1, 1993. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Major Owens, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Hulett Pankey, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 30, Box 9, Cassette 50)
  Hulett S. Pankey was born in 1903 in Brooklyn, New York. He was a member of Vincent Carney's political club along with his brother Robert Pankey. Pankey died on January 17, 1991.
  This interview took place on November 4, 1989. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Lawrence Pierce [and Cynthia Straker], 1988 (Box 4, Folder 31, Box 9, Cassette 51, Cassette 52, Cassette 53)
  Lawrence "Larry" Pierce was born on December 31, 1924 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Pierce served in World War II and received his undergraduate degree from St. Joseph's University in Philadelphia. Pierce moved to New York City in 1948 to start law school at Fordham University. He graduated in 1951 and lived in Harlem in Manhattan. He then moved to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  He was appointed to the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of New York by President Richard Nixon in 1971 and in 1981 was appointed by Ronald Reagan to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit. Lawrence Pierce married Cynthia Straker in 1979 after his first wife died. He retired from the bench in 1995 and served as director of the United States Agency for International Development (USAID)-funded Cambodian Court Training Project. He died on February 5, 2020.
  Cynthia Straker was born on July 20, 1929 in Brooklyn, New York. She graduated from Hunter College and received her law degree from Brooklyn Law School. She worked as a lawyer with the office of the general counsel of the Department of Transportation and for the Federal Aviation Administration in Washington, DC. She married Lawrence Pierce in 1979. Straker taught at Howard University and Fordham University Law School. Straker died on November 30, 2011.
  This interview took place on May 21, 1988. Cynthia Straker is also a part of the interview. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Lawrence Pierce, 1988-1992 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Jerald E. Podair, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  This file contains two papers by Jerald E. Podair titled "'We Speak Different Languages': The Ocean Hill-Brownsville Controversy and the Fall of New York City's Liberal Consensus, 1960-1970" and "'White' Values, 'Black' Values: The Ocean Hill-Brownsville Controversy and New York City Culture, 1965-1975."
- Wendell E. Pritchett, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Elsie Richardson, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Anne M. Roberts, 1964-1971 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Jackie Robinson, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- J. Mitchell Rosenberg, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 1, Box 9, Cassette 54, Cassette 55)
  J. Mitchell Rosenberg was born on August 26, 1906 in Bayonne, New Jersey. His father was a rabbi and they moved several times while he was growing up. They came to Brooklyn when he was 16, living in Borough Park and then finally Flatbush. Rosenberg graduated from Columbia University Law School. He was a member of the Flatbush Hesterberg Democratic Club and served as Assistant District Attorney in Kings County. Rosenberg died on March 15, 2000.
  This interview took place on December 7, 1989. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Murray Rosenberg, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 2, Box 10, Cassette 1, Cassette 2)
  Murray Rosenberg was born on June 5, 1925 in Brooklyn, New York. He started classes at City College in New York, but paused in 1941 to join the U.S. Army. After World War II, he returned to Brownsville in Brooklyn where his parents lived and completed his degree at City College. He was a member of the Unity Democratic Club, worked for the New York City Welfare Department (now the Department of Social Services), and was active in the union. He also worked as an advertising copywriter. Rosenberg died in 2003.
  This interview took place on May 11, 1988. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Burton Rudnick, circa 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Herbert Ryan, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 4, Box 10, Cassette 3)
  Herbert Ryan was born on August 10, 1931 in Long Branch, New Jersey. He grew up in Queens and then moved to Sunset Park in Brooklyn in 1959. Ryan served in the Korean War and received his law degree from St. John's University. Ryan continued service in several positions in the New York National Guard and the Army Reserve as well as holding several civil government positions, including First Deputy City Clerk. He also taught at St. John's University. Ryan died on June 17, 2022.
  This interview took place on December 22, 1987. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- St. Francis College Kelly Institute, circa 1987 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Leonard Scholnick, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 6, Box 10, Cassette 4)
  Leonard Scholnick was a former leader of the 4th Assembly District Democratic Club, also known as the Seneca Political Club (started in 1899) in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. He attended Brooklyn College and New York Law School and was admitted to the Bar in 1958. Scholnick served as Assistant District Attorney in Brooklyn 1958-1959, then went into private practice. He was a New York State Supreme Court Justice in Kings County, elected in 1972.
  This interview took place on July 1, 1987. The second half of the interview may have taken place on a different date. Audio related to this interview includes Jeffrey Gerson's comments after the meeting. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
  Jeffrey Gerson's audio comments are in one preservation .WAV file and one access .mp3 file.
- Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  This file contains an article titled "The Schomburg" by Sharon Fitzgerald published in American Visions.
- Josephine Scott, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 8-9, Box 10, Cassette 5, Cassette 6, Cassette 7, Cassette 8)
  Josephine "Jo" Scott was a former longtime member and secretary of Bertram Baker's United Action Democratic Club in Brooklyn. At the time of the interview Josephine Scott worked in advertising at Young and Rubicam.
  Scott was born on September 8, 1921 in Bedford-Stuyvesant, 201 Hancock Street, Brooklyn. Her father was born in Richmond, Virginia and mother was from Brooklyn. Her grandmother owned a bakery at 432 Franklin Avenue. Josephine Scott died on March 23, 2006.
  This interview took place on July 23, 1988 at Josephine Scott's home in Suffolk County, Long Island, New York. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  Four original audio cassettes.
- Joseph T. Sharkey [and Helen Flaherty Sharkey], 1987 (Box 5, Folder 10, Box 10, Cassette 9, Cassette 10, Cassette 11, Cassette 12)
  Joseph T. Sharkey was born on January 12, 1893 in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. His parents were both from Brooklyn and were involved with the Democratic Party in Brooklyn. After serving in World War I and working for the city in various positions, Sharkey was elected to the Board of Aldermen (the predecessor to the New York City Council) in 1933. He served on the Council until 1961 and was President (1949-1951) and Council Majority Leader (1940-1961).
  Sharkey married Helen Flaherty in 1935 and they had three daughters.
  After leaving the New York City Council, Sharkey was President of the Dime Savings Bank until his retirement in 1975. He died on January 2, 1991.
  Helen Flaherty was born on December 27, 1903 in Brooklyn. She married Joseph T. Sharkey in 1935 and they had three daughters. She died on September 12, 1996.
  Jeffrey Gerson conducted two interviews with Joseph Sharkey on October 7 and October 23, 1987 at his home in Brooklyn. Helen Flaherty Sharkey joined the second interview. Both interviews have an accompanying transcript.
  Eight preservation .WAV files. Eight access .mp3 files.
- Joseph T. Sharkey, 1987-1991 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- James Shaw, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 12, Box 10, Cassette 13, Cassette 16)
  James "Jim" H. Shaw, Jr. was born on September 24, 1923 in Birmingham, Alabama. He came to New York City in the summer of 1942 and attended Fordham University Law School. In 1942, Shaw entered the military during World War II. Shaw was a member of Bertram Baker's United Action Democratic Club, elected to State Senate in 1965 and was a State Supreme Court judge from Brooklyn. The New York State Commission on Judicial Conduct censured Shaw in 1999 for sexual harrassment. Shaw retired soon after.
  This interview took place on June 7, 1988. James H. Shaw discusses the history of Black politics in Brooklyn and New York City. This interview has an accompanying transcript.
- Daphne Sheppard, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 13, Box 10, Cassette 14)
  Daphne A. Sheppard was born in 1917. She was manager of the Brooklyn office of the Amsterdam News for 25 years starting around 1950 and wrote a regular column called "Kings Diary," which chronicled events in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Ocean Hill, and Brownsville. She also worked as an Assistant Administrator for the Model Cities Program in the Mayor's Office in the 1960s. She lived in Crown Heights at the time of this interview. Sheppard died in 2006.
  This interview took place on September 27, 1989. Side 2 of this interview may be missing. This interview does not have an accompanying transcript.
- Charles Sherwood, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 14, Box 9, Cassette 8, Box 10, Cassette 15, Cassette 16)
  Charles L. Sherwood was born on December 9, 1900 in Kingston, Jamaica. He moved to the United States in August 1923 to study dentistry. He first lived in Harlem in Manhattan and then moved to Bedford-Stuyvesant in Brooklyn in 1941. Sherwood was a member of Bertram Baker's United Action Democratic Club. He died in 2000.
  This interview took place on June 7, 1988. This interview does not have an accompanying transcript.
- I. Philip Sipser, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 15, Box 10, Cassette 17)
  Isidore Philip Sipser was born September 2, 1918 on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. His family later moved to Brooklyn and Sipser went to Brooklyn College and Brooklyn Law School. Sipser ran for New York State Senate in 1944 and New York State Assembly in 1947 and 1948 on the American Labor Party ticket, but lost the elections. He was also manager for Paul O'Dwyer's unsuccessful 1968 campaign for U.S. Senate against Jacob K. Javits.
  Outside of politics, Sipser worked as a labor lawyer and was known for representing musicians. Sipser died March 31, 2001.
  This interview took place on April 28, 1988. This interview has an accompanying transcript.
- Nathan Sobel, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 16, Box 10, Cassette 18, Cassette 19)
  Sobel was born on May 13, 1906 on the Lower East Side of Manhattan to Russian parents. His family moved to Brooklyn and he grew up in the Borough Park and Brownsville neighborhoods. Sobel graduated from Boys High School and entered Brooklyn Law School at age 15. After passing the bar, he began working in legal counsel positions and judgeships in New York State. He sat on the Supreme Court in Brooklyn and the Brooklyn Surrogate Court.
  Sobel retired in 1976 and continued some pro bono legal work. Sobel never married and lived in Brooklyn Heights during his professional and later life. Sobel died on May 20, 1997.
  This interview took place on August 19, 1987. This interview does not have an accompanying transcript.
- Stephen Solarz, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Mark T. Southall, circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Sidney Squire, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 19, Box 10, Cassette 20, Cassette 21, Cassette 22, Cassette 23)
  Sidney Squire was born on December 27, 1906 in Manhattan to Russian parents. They moved to Flatbush in Brooklyn when Squire was a boy. Squire attended City College and then Brooklyn Law School. He enlisted in the Army during World War II and began working in a private practice, Squire and Leavitt, on his return. Squire was an advisor to Brooklyn district leader and Assemblyman Bertram L. Baker. Squire was senior judge on the New York State Court of Claims from 1956 until he retired from the bench in 1977. He continued working in private practice until 1996. Squire died on February 12, 1997.
  Sidney Squire was interviewed twice on September 21, 1989 and October 4, 1989. These interviews do not have accompanying transcripts.
- Biographical sketch of Abe Stark, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Stanley Steingut, 1985-1989 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Stanley Steingut, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 22, Box 10, Cassette 24)
  Stanley Steingut was born on May 20, 1920 in Crown Heights in Brooklyn. He attended Union College and then served in the Navy during World War II. He received his law degree from St. John's University Law School.
  Steingut's father, Irwin Steingut, was a Democratic Assemblyman from Brooklyn from 1930-1952 when Stanley succeeded him. He served in the New York State Assembly from 1952 to to 1978 and was speaker and minority leader for a time. He was a leader of the Kings County Democratic organization and the Madison Democratic Club in Crown Heights. Steingut also had a private practice, Berger and Steingut.
  Steingut married Madeline Fellerman and they had two sons. Steingut died in 1989.
  This interview took place on December 6, 1985. This interview has an accompanying transcript.
- Harvey Strelzin, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 23, Box 10, Cassette 25, Cassette 26)
  Harvey L. Strelzin was born on July 19, 1906 and raised in Brooklyn. He attended City College, Brooklyn Law School, and New York Law School. Strelzin served as Assistant Attorney General and was elected to the New York State Assembly for District 57 in Brooklyn. He was on the Assembly from 1969 to 1980. Strelzin taught at Brooklyn College and New York Law School. He was chairman of the Federation of Jewish Philanthropies and of the Israel Bond Drives. He died on December 8, 1993.
  This interview took place on October 17, 1987. This interview has an accompanying transcript.
- Percy Sutton, 1967-1974 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Gardner Taylor, 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 25, Box 10, Cassette 27, Cassette 28)
  Gardner Calvin Taylor was born on June 18, 1918 in Baton Rouge, Louisiana. He graduated from the Oberlin College School of Theology in 1940 and was a pastor at a few other churches until 1948 when he became head of the Concord Baptist Church of Christ in Bedford-Stuyvesant in Brooklyn. Mayor Robert F. Wagner, Jr. appointed Taylor to the New York City Board of Education on which he served for three years. Mayor Wagner also asked him to fill in on the Kings County Democratic County Committee while looking for a replacement for Joseph T. Sharkey. He helped found the Progressive National Baptist Convention in 1961.
  Taylor stayed at Concord Baptist Church until he retired in 1990 and moved to North Carolina. He died on April 5, 2015.
  This interview took place on July 7, 1988. The audio related to this interview includes Jeffrey Gerson's comments after the interview. This interview has an accompanying transcript.
- Bob Teague, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  This file contains an article titled "Charlie Doesn't Even Know His Daily Racism is a Sick Joke" by Bob Teague.
- Franklin A. Thomas, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 27 - 28)
- William Thompson, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 29, Box 10, Cassette 29)
  William "Willie" C. Thompson, Sr. was born on October 26, 1924 in Harlem in Manhattan. A couple years later, his family moved to Brooklyn. Thompson attended Brooklyn College for his undergraduate and law degrees. He served in the Army during World War II.
  Thompson was a New York State Senator from 1965-1968 and then a member of the New York City Council from 1969-1973. He was elected to the New York Supreme Court in 1973. He retired from the bench on January 1, 2001. Thompson died on December 24, 2018. Bill Thompson, former New York City Comptroller from 2002-2009, is his son.